When I was 14 years old, I was interested in science --
حين كنت فى الرابعة عشر , كنت مهتمة بالعلوم--
fascinated by it, excited to learn about it.
مغرمة به .متشوقة أن أتعلمه.
And I had a high school science teacher who would say to the class,
وكان لدي مدرس علوم في المدرسة الثانوية يقول للفصل،
"The girls don't have to listen to this."
ّالفتيات ليس عليهن الاستماع لذلك. "
Encouraging, yes.
ذلك مًشجّع، نعم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I chose not to listen -- but to that statement alone.
واخترت ألا أستمع -- ولكن لتلك العبارة فقط.
So let me take you to the Andes mountains in Chile,
لذا دعوني آخذكم إلى جبال الانديز في شيلي
500 kilometers, 300 miles northeast of Santiago.
على بعد 500 كم و300ميل من شمال شرق سانتياغو
It's very remote, it's very dry and it's very beautiful.
إنها بعيدة جدا وجافة جدا وجميلة جدا
And there's not much there.
ولا يوجد هناك الكثير.
There are condors, there are tarantulas,
هناك نسور الكوندور والترانتولا،
and at night, when the light dims,
وفي الليل عندما يكون الضوء خافتا
it reveals one of the darkest skies on Earth.
يتم الكشف عن أظلم السماوات على وجه الأرض.
It's kind of a magic place, the mountain.
إنه شبيه بمكان ساحر، الجبل.
It's a wonderful combination of very remote mountaintop
انه مزيج رائع من قمة الجبل المعزولة
with exquisitely sophisticated technology.
مع التكنولوجيا المتطورة الرائعة
And our ancestors, for as long as there's been recorded history,
وأجدادنا، لطالما كان هناك تاريخ مسجل،
have looked at the night sky and pondered the nature of our existence.
قد نظروا إلى السماء وتأملوا حقيقية وجودنا.
And we're no exception, our generation.
وجيلنا ليس باستثناء.
The only difficulty is that the night sky now is blocked
الصعوبة الوحيدة هي أن السماء ليلا أصبحت محجوبة
by the glare of city lights.
بسبب وهج أضواء المدينة.
And so astronomers go to these very remote mountaintops
ولذلك يذهب علماء الفلك إلى قمم تلك الجبال البعيدة
to view and to study the cosmos.
لمشاهدة ودراسة الكون.
So telescopes are our window to the cosmos.
لذلك فان التيلسكوب هو شباكنا الذي نشاهد عبره الكون.
It's no exaggeration to say that the Southern Hemisphere is going to be
ليس هناك مبالغة اذا قلنا أن نصف الكرة الجنوبي سيكون
the future of astronomy for the 21st century.
هو مستقبل علم الفلك فى القرن21
We have an array of existing telescopes already,
ولدينا بالفعل مجموعة من المناظير
in the Andes mountains in Chile,
في جبال الانديز في شيلي
and that's soon to be joined by a really sensational array of new capability.
وسينضم إليها قريبا مجموعة مثيرة لها قدرات جديدة
There will be two international groups that are going to be building
وسيكون هناك مجموعتان دوليتان ستقومان ببناء
giant telescopes, sensitive to optical radiation, as our eyes are.
مناظير ضخمة حساسة للإشعاع الضوئي كأعيننا.
There will be a survey telescope
سيكون هناك منظار للاستطلاع
that will be scanning the sky every few nights.
الذي سيقوم بفحص السماء كل عدة ليالي
There will be radio telescopes,
سيكون هناك مناظير لاسلكية
sensitive to long-wavelength radio radiation.
حساسة للأشعة ذات الموجات الطويلة
And then there will be telescopes in space.
وسيكون هناك منظار في الفضاء.
There'll be a successor to the Hubble Space Telescope;
وسيكون هناك خليفة لمنظار الفضاء(هابل)
it's called the James Webb Telescope,
ويطلق عليه منظار جيمس ويب،
and it will be launched in 2018.
وسيتم إصداره عام 2018.
There'll be a satellite called TESS
وسيكون هناك قمر صناعى يدعى تيس
that will discover planets outside of our solar system.
والذي سيكتشف الكواكب خارج المجموعة الشمسية.
For the last decade, I've been leading a group --
في العشر سنوات الاخيرة توليت قيادة مجموعة
a consortium -- international group,
اتحاد -- مجموعة دولية،
to build what will be, when it's finished,
لبناء ماسوف يكون عليه، عند انتهائه،
the largest optical telescope in existence.
أكبر منظار ضوئى في الوجود.
It's called the Giant Magellan Telescope, or GMT.
ويسمى منظار ماجلان العملاق (GMT).
This telescope is going to have mirrors that are 8.4 meters in diameter --
هذا المنظار سيكون له مرايا قطرها حوالى8.4 م
each of the mirrors.
كل مرآة من المرا يا
That's almost 27 feet.
والتى تقدر ب27 قدم تقريبا.
So it dwarfs this stage -- maybe out to the fourth row in this audience.
لذا فهو يصغر هذا المسرح ربما للصف الرابع من الجمهور.
Each of the seven mirrors in this telescope
كل مرآة من السبع مرايا في هذا المنظار
will be almost 27 feet in diameter.
سيكون قطرها حوالي 27 قدم.
Together, the seven mirrors in this telescope will comprise
وكل هذه المرايا السبع معا فى هذا المنظار
80 feet in diameter.
سيكون قطرها 80 قدما.
So, essentially the size of this entire auditorium.
اذن أساسا في الحجم الكلي لهذه القاعة.
The whole telescope will stand about 43 meters high,
سيكون المنظار على ارتفاع 43مترا
and again, being in Rio,
ومرة أخرى - كونه في ريو-
some of you have been to see the statue of the giant Christ.
بعضكم سيكون قادرا علي رؤية تمثال المسيح العظيم.
The scale is comparable in height;
والحجم لا يقارن في الارتفاع
in fact, it's smaller than this telescope will be.
في الواقع هو أصغر مما سيكون عليه هذا المنظار
It's comparable to the size of the Statue of Liberty.
وهو يقارن بحجم تمثال الحرية.
And it's going to be housed in an enclosure that's 22 stories --
وسيكون مقره في منطقة مسيجة
60 meters high.
وارتفاعها 60 م.
But it's an unusual building to protect this telescope.
ولكنه مبنى غير عادي لحماية ذلك المنظار.
It will have open windows to the sky,
سيكون له شبابيك مفتوحة علي السماء.
be able to point and look at the sky,
قادر على الإشارة والنظر إلى السماء.
and it will actually rotate on a base --
وسيدور فعليا علي قاعدة --
2,000 tons of rotating building.
وزنها 2000 طن من المبنى الدوار.
The Giant Magellan Telescope will have 10 times the resolution
منظار ماجلان العملاق سيكون 10 مرات أدق
of the Hubble Space Telescope.
من منظار الفضاء هابل.
It will be 20 million times more sensitive than the human eye.
ستكون حساسيته 20 مليون مرة أكثر من العين البشرية
And it may, for the first time ever, be capable of finding life on planets
وربما يكون ولأول مرة قادرا على إيجاد حياة على سطح الكواكب الأخرى
outside of our solar system.
خارج نطاق المجموعة الشمسية.
It's going to allow us to look back at the first light in the universe --
سيسمح لنا بالرجوع للنظر في مصدر أول ضوء في الكون --
literally, the dawn of the cosmos.
وأعني حرفيا بداية الكون.
The cosmic dawn.
بداية الكون.
It's a telescope that's going to allow us to peer back,
إنه المنظار الذى سيتيح لنا إمعان النظر مرة أخرى،
witness galaxies as they were when they were actually assembling,
وأن نشهد المجرات كما كانت عندما تم تجميعها،
the first black holes in the universe, the first galaxies.
الثقوب السوداء الأولى في الكون والمجرات الأولى.
Now, for thousands of years, we have been studying the cosmos,
إلى حد الآن درسنا الكون لآلاف السنين،
we've been wondering about our place in the universe.
تساءلنا عن موقعنا في هذا الكون.
The ancient Greeks told us
ولقد أخبرنا اليونانيون القدامى
that the Earth was the center of the universe.
أن الأرض هي مركز الكون.
Five hundred years ago, Copernicus displaced the Earth,
ومنذ 500 سنه قام كوبرنيكوس بإزاحة الأرض،
and put the Sun at the heart of the cosmos.
ووضع الشمس في قلب الكون.
And as we've learned over the centuries,
وكما تعلمنا على مدار القرون،
since Galileo Galilei, the Italian scientist,
منذ أن قام جاليلي، العالم الإيطالي،
first turned, in that time, a two-inch, very small telescope, to the sky,
لأول مرة فى ذلك الوقت بادارة منظار صغير جدا حجمه 2 بوصة في السماء،
every time we have built larger telescopes,
وفي كل مرة نقوم فيها ببناء منظار أكبر،
we have learned something about the universe;
نكتشف شيئا جديدا حول الكون،
we've made discoveries, without exception.
لقد قمنا باكتشافات بدون استثناء،
We've learned in the 20th century that the universe is expanding
ولقد تعلمنا في القرن ال20 أن الكون يتسع
and that our own solar system is not at the center of that expansion.
وأن مجموعتنا الشمسية ليست مركز ذلك التوسع.
We know now that the universe is made of about 100 billion galaxies
ولقد علمنا الآن أن الكون يتكون من 100 بليون مجرة
that are visible to us,
والتى يمكننا رؤيتها،
and each one of those galaxies has 100 billion stars within it.
وكل مجرة من تلك المجرات بداخلها 100بليون نجم.
So we're looking now at the deepest image of the cosmos
الآن نحن ننظر الى أعمق صورة للكون
that's ever been taken.
والتي تم التقاطها.
It was taken using the Hubble Space Telescope,
تم التقاطها بمنظار الفضاء هابل
and by pointing the telescope at what was previously a blank region of sky,
وبتوجيه المنظار إلى مكان في السماء كان خاليا سابقا،
before the launch of Hubble.
قبل إطلاق هابيل.
And if you can imagine this tiny area,
وإن كان في إمكانك تخيل تلك المنطقة الصغيرة،
it's only one-fiftieth of the size of the full moon.
إنها بقدر 5 مرات حجم القمر مكتملا.
So, if you can imagine the full moon.
لذا إن كان في امكانك تخيل حجم القمر كاملا.
And there are now 10,000 galaxies visible within that image.
ويوجد الآن 10000 مجرة مرئية داخل هذه الصورة.
of the fact that those galaxies are so far away, the vast distances.
لبعد تلك المجرات والمسافة الكبيرة بينها.
Telescopes are like time machines.
لذلك فكلما نظرنا بعيدا في الفضاء كلما شاهدنا بعيدا فى الزمن.
So the farther back we look in space, the further back we see in time.
فهى كسلات للضوء حرفيا تجمع الضوء.
And they're like light buckets -- literally, they collect light.
لذلك كلما كبرت السلة، كلما كانت المرآة اكبر،
So larger the bucket, the larger the mirror we have,
كلما رأينا ضوء أكثر وكلما شاهدنا أبعد.
the more light we can see, and the farther back we can view.
لذلك فقد تعلمنا في القرن الأخير
So, we've learned in the last century
أنه يوجد أشياء غريبة في الكون -الثقوب السوداء.
that there are exotic objects in the universe -- black holes.
وتعلمنا أنه يوجد ماد ظلمة وطاقة ظلمة
We've even learned that there's dark matter and dark energy
والتي لا يمكننا رؤيتها.
that we can't see.
لذلك فأنتم تنظرون الأن لصورة فعلية لشيء أظلم.
So you're looking now at an actual image of dark matter.
(ضحك)
(Laughter)
لقد فهمتموها. ليس الجميع بين الجمهور قد فهم ذلك.
You got it. Not all audiences get that.
(ضحك)
So the way we infer the presence of dark matter --
لا يمكن رؤيته ولكن يوجد سحب واضح بسبب الجاذبية.
we can't see it -- but there's an unmistakable tug, due to gravity.
ونستطيع الآن النظر ورؤية المجرات
We now can look out, we see this sea of galaxies
في الكون الذى يتمدد.
in a universe that's expanding.
وما أفعله بنفسي هو قياس التمدد في الكون،
What I do myself is to measure the expansion of the universe,
ومن المشاريع التي قمت بها خلال التسعينات
and one of the projects that I carried out in the 1990s
استخدام منظار هابل للفضاء لقياس مدى تمدد الكون.
used the Hubble Space Telescope to measure how fast the universe is expanding.
يمكننا الآن الرجوع بالزمن مدة 14 بليون سنة.
We can now trace back to 14 billion years.
ولقد تعلمنا على مدار الزمن أن للنجوم تواريخ شخصية،
We've learned over time that stars have individual histories;
أي أن لها ميلاد ومنتصف عمر
that is, they have birth, they have middle ages
وأن لبعضها موت درامي.
and some of them even have dramatic deaths.
لذلك فالجمرات الناتجة عن هذه النجوم تكون بالفعل نجوم جديدة نراها،
So the embers from those stars actually then form the new stars that we see,
ومعظمها يكون له كواكب تدور حوله.
most of which turn out to have planets going around them.
وكان من النتائج المدهشة حقا في العشرين سنة الأخيرة
And one of the really surprising results in the last 20 years
التي تم اكتشافها أن كواكب أخرى تدور حول نجوم أخرى.
has been the discovery of other planets going around other stars.
وهذه تسمى الكواكب الخارجية.
These are called exoplanets.
وحتى عام 1995 لم نكن نعرف عن وجود أي كواكب أخرى،
And until 1995, we didn't even know the existence of any other planets,
غير تلك التي تدور حول الشمس.
other than going around our own sun.
ولكن الآن يوجد 2000 كوكب آخر يدور حول نجوم أخرى
that we can now detect, measure masses for.
والتى يمكننا كشفها وقياس كتلتها.
There are 500 of those that are multiple-planet systems.
ويوجد500 من هذه الكواكب متعددة الأنظمة.
And there are 4,000 -- and still counting -- other candidates
ويوجد 400 -- في ازدياد --
for planets orbiting other stars.
كوكب يدور حول نجوم أخرى.
They come in a bewildering variety of different kinds.
ولقد اتوا فى تشكيلات متنوعة.
There are Jupiter-like planets that are hot,
توجد كواكب أخرى حارة شبيهة بكوكب المشتري،
there are other planets that are icy, there are water worlds
هناك كواكب أخرى جليدية، ويوجد عوالم من المياه
and there are rocky planets like the Earth, so-called "super-Earths,"
وهناك كواكب صخرية مثل الأرض وتسمى "بالأرض الممتازة"،
and there have even been planets that have been speculated diamond worlds.
,وهناك كواكب التى كان من المعتقد أنها مصادر غنية بالألماس.
So we know there's at least one planet, our own Earth, in which there is life.
وعلمنا أنه يوجد كوكب واحد فقط عليه حياة وهو كوكب الأرض.
We've even found planets that are orbiting two stars.
وجدنا كواكب تدور حول نجمين.
That's no longer the province of science fiction.
لم يعد هناك مجال للخيال العلمي.
So around our own planet, we know there's life,
لذلك حول كوكبنا نعلم أنه هناك حياة،
we've developed a complex life, we now can question our own origins.
لقد طورنا حياة معقدة، ويمكننا الآن أن نسأل عن أصولنا.
And given all that we've discovered, the overwhelming numbers now suggest
وبالافصاح عما اكتشفناه فان الأعداد الهائلة تخمن
that there may be millions, perhaps -- maybe even hundreds of millions --
بأنه يوجد الملايين بل مئات الملايين
of other [planets] that are close enough --
من النجوم الأخرى القريبة بدرجة كافية --
just the right distance from their stars that they're orbiting --
فقط المسافة المناسبة بينهم وبين النجوم التى يدورون حولها
to have the existence of liquid water and maybe could potentially support life.
وفيها مياه سائلة وربما تدعم الحياة.
So we marvel now at those odds, the overwhelming odds,
لذا نتعجب من كل تلك الأشياء الغريبة،
and the amazing thing is that within the next decade,
والشيئ المدهش أنه خلال العقد القادم،
the GMT may be able to take spectra of the atmospheres of those planets,
وال(GMT) قادر على أخذ أطياف الغلاف الجوي لهذه الكواكب،
and determine whether or not they have the potential for life.
ومعرفة ما إذا كان هناك إمكانية حديث.
So, what is the GMT project?
إذن فما هو مشروع (GMT)?
It's an international project.
إنه مشروع دولى.
It includes Australia, South Korea, and I'm happy to say, being here in Rio,
ويتضمن استراليا وكوريا الجنوبية ويسعدني القول- وأنا هنا في كوريا،
that the newest partner in our telescope is Brazil.
أن شريكنا الجديد في المنظار هي البرازيل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It also includes a number of institutions across the United States,
ويتضمن أيضا عددا من المعاهد بالولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
including Harvard University,
يتضمن جامعة هارفارد،
the Smithsonian and the Carnegie Institutions,
المعاهد السمثسونية والكارنيجية،
and the Universities of Arizona, Chicago, Texas-Austin and Texas A&amp;M University.
وجامعات اريزونا وشيكاغو وتكساس اوستن وتكساس.
It also involves Chile.
وتتضمن أيضا الشيلي.
So, the making of the mirrors in this telescope is also fascinating
لذلك فان صنع المرايا فى هذا التلسكوب شىئ مذهل
in its own right.
فى حد ذاته.
Take chunks of glass, melt them in a furnace that is itself rotating.
خذ قطع من الزجاج ثم قم بإذابتها فى فرن دائر بنفسه.
This happens underneath the football stadium
هذا يتم تحت استاد كرة القدم
at the University of Arizona.
في جامعة اريزونا.
It's tucked away under 52,000 seats.
ويتم إخفاءه تحت 52,000 مقعد.
Nobody know it's happening.
لا أحد يعلم أن ذلك يحدث.
And there's essentially a rotating cauldron.
ويوجد أساسا مرجل دوار.
The mirrors are cast and they're cooled very slowly,
ويتم صب المرايا الذائبة وتبريدها شيئا فشيئا،
and then they're polished to an exquisite precision.
وتم صقلها بدقة رائعة.
And so, if you think about the precision of these mirrors,
إذن إذا فكرت في دقة المرايا،
the bumps on the mirror, over the entire 27 feet,
النتوءات علي مرآة -اكثر من 27 قدم-
amount to less than one-millionth of an inch.
اقل من واحد على مليون من ا لبوصة.
So, can you visualize that?
لذ ا هل يمكنك رؤيتها؟
Ow!
أو
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's one five-thousandths of the width of one of my hairs,
ذلك واحد على 5000 من عرض شعرة من شعري،
over this entire 27 feet.
على 27 قدم كامل.
It's a spectacular achievement.
إنه إنجاز مذهل.
It's what allows us to have the precision that we will have.
وهو ما يسمح لنا بالحصول على الدقة المطلوبة.
So, what does that precision buy us?
إذن، ماهي الفائدة من تلك الدقة؟
So the GMT, if you can imagine --
لذا فان (GMT) لو تخيلتوا --
if I were to hold up a coin, which I just happen to have,
لورفعت عملة معدنية لدي،
and I look at the face of that coin, I can see from here
ونظرت إلى وجه العملة، يمكننى من هنا رؤية
the writing on the coin; I can see the face on that coin.
الكتابة على العملة أستطيع رؤية وجه العملة.
My guess that even in the front row, you can't see that.
وضيوفنا في الصف الأول، لا تستطيعون رؤية ذلك.
But if we were to turn the Giant Magellan Telescope,
ولكن اذا قلبنا منظار ماجلان العملاق،
all 80-feet diameter that we see in this auditorium,
فان قاعة المحاضرات التى قطرها 80 قدم
and point it 200 miles away,
وببعدها 200 ميل
if I were standing in São Paulo, we could resolve the face of this coin.
لو وقفت في سانبولو يمكننا رؤية وجه العملة.
That's the extraordinary resolution and power of this telescope.
تلك هى دقة المنظار الفائقة.
And if we were --
ولو كنا --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If an astronaut went up to the Moon, a quarter of a million miles away,
لو صعد رائد فضاء للقمر علي بعد ربع مليون ميل،
and lit a candle -- a single candle --
وأشعل شمعة -- شمعة واحدة --
then we would be able to detect it, using the GMT.
يمكننا رؤيتها بالمنظار، باستعمال GMT،
Quite extraordinary.
شيئ ممتاز حقا.
This is a simulated image of a cluster in a nearby galaxy.
تلك صورة محاكية لتجمع بمجرة قريبة.
"Nearby" is astronomical, it's all relative.
إن "كلمة قريبة " كلمة فلكية كلها نسبية.
It's tens of millions of light-years away.
انها تبعد 10 ملايين سنة ضوئية.
This is what this cluster would look like.
هذا هو شكل ذك التجمع.
So look at those four bright objects,
لذا انظروا إلى تلك الأجسام الأربعة،
and now lets compare it with a camera on the Hubble Space Telescope.
والآن لنقارنهم بكاميراعلى منظار هابل.
You can see faint detail that starts to come through.
يمكنكم رؤية تفاصيل صغيرة والتى بدأت في الظهور.
And now finally -- and look how dramatic this is -- this is what the GMT will see.
وفى النهاية _وانظروا كيف تبدو دراماتيكية - هذا ما سيراه GMT.
So, keep your eyes on those bright images again.
لذا ركز عينيك على هذه الصور اللامعة.
This is what we see on one of the most powerful existing telescopes on the Earth,
ذلك ما سنراه باستعمال أحد أفضل المناظير على الأرض،
and this, again, what the GMT will see.
وهذا للمرة الثانية ماسنراه بالمنظار.
Extraordinary precision.
دقة فائقة.
So, where are we?
إذن أين نحن؟
We have now leveled the top of the mountaintop in Chile.
نحن الآن على قمة جبل فى شيلي.
We blasted that off.
لقد فجرناه.
We've tested and polished the first mirror.
لقد اختبرنا و صقلنا ا لمرآة الأولى.
We've cast the second and the third mirrors.
والقينا المرايا الثانية والثالثة.
And we're about to cast the fourth mirror.
وعلي وشك القاء الرابعة.
We had a series of reviews this year,
لدينا مجموعة من المراجعات هذا العام
international panels that came in and reviewed us,
طائرات دولية ستحضر وتقوم بفحصنا،
and said, "You're ready to go to construction."
ويقولون "نحن على استعداد للذهاب للبناء"
And so we plan on building this telescope with the first four mirrors.
ولذلك خططنا لبناء ذلك التلسكوب باستخدام الأربع مرايا الأولى.
We want to get on the air quickly, and be taking science data --
نريد الارتفاع فى الهواء بسرعة، وجمع بيانات علمية --
what we astronomers call "first light," in 2021.
لما نسميه كعلماء الفلك ّّالضوء الأوّل عام2021.
And the full telescope will be finished in the middle of the next decade,
وسيتم الإنتهاء من التلسكوب الثاني في منتصف العقد الموالي،
with all seven mirrors.
باستخدام المرايا السبعة.
So we're now poised to look back at the distant universe,
لذا فنحن ننظر الى الكون المستقبلي،
the cosmic dawn.
الفجر الكونى.
We'll be able to study other planets in exquisite detail.
سنكون قادرين على دراسة الكواكب الاخرى بتفاصيل رائعة.
But for me, one of the most exciting things about building the GMT
بالنسبة لي، فمن أكثر الأشياء إثارة في بناء التيلسكوب
is the opportunity to actually discover something
هو فرصة اكتشاف شيء ما
that we don't know about -- that we can't even imagine at this point,
لا نعلم عنه شيء والذى لم نكن نتخيله في هذه المرحلة،
something completely new.
شيء ما جديد تماما.
And my hope is that with the construction of this and other facilities,
وأملي أنه مع بناء هذا التلسكوب وغيره من التسهيلات،
that many young women and men will be inspired to reach for the stars.
فالعديد من الرجال والنساء سيتوقون للوصول إلى النجوم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
Obrigado.
أوبريغادو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Wendy.
برونو غييساني: شكرا ويندي.
Stay with me, because I have a question for you.
ابقي معي لدي سؤال لك.
You mentioned different facilities.
ذكرتم تسهيلات مختلفة.
So the Magellan Telescope is going up, but also ALMA and others in Chile
لذا فان تلسكوب متجلان يصعد ولكن أيضا الما وآخرون في شيلى
and elsewhere, including in Hawaii.
وأماكن أخرى بما فيها هواي.
Is it about cooperation and complementarity, or about competition?
هل ذلك دليل على التعاون والتكامل أو المناقسة؟
I know there's competition in terms of funding, but what about the science?
اعرف ان هناك منافسة من حيث التمويل ولكن ماذا عن العلم؟؟؟؟؟؟
Wendy Freedman: In terms of the science, they're very complementary.
وندى فريدمان: بالمصطلحات العلمية هم متكاملون جدا.
The telescopes that are in space, the telescopes on the ground,
التلسكوب الذي في الفضاء، والتلسكوب الذي على الارض،
telescopes with different wavelength capability,
تلسكوبات ذات قدرات ذات موجات مختلفة،
telescopes even that are similar, but different instruments --
تلسكوبات متشابهة لكنها أدوات مختلفة تماما --
they will all look at different parts of the questions that we're asking.
كل سينظر من جهة مختلفة للأسئلة التي طرحناها.
So when we discover other planets, we'll be able to test those observations,
لذا عندما نكتشف كواكب أخرى سنكون قادرين على اختبار تلك الملاحظات
we'll be able to measure the atmospheres,
سنتمكن من قياس الغلاف الجوي،
be able to look in space with very high resolution.
سنتمكن من النظر فى الفضاء بدرجة وضوح عالية.
So, they're very complementary.
لذا فهم متكاملون تماما.
You're right about the funding, we compete;
أنت محق بخصوص التمويل فنحن نتنافس،
but scientifically, it's very complementary.
ولكن من الناحية العلمية فهي متكاملة.
BG: Wendy, thank you very much for coming to TEDGlobal.
شكرا لكي وندي لحضورك إلى محاضرة تيد TEDGlobal
WF: Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)